<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Reading, Feb. 25, 1672, at the assizes there holden for the county of Berks, before the Right Honourable Sir Edward Turner, Knight ... and Sir Edward Thurland, Knight ... by Joseph Sayer ...</title>
            <author>Sayer, Joseph, 1630 or 31-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13242015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13242015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 438:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Reading, Feb. 25, 1672, at the assizes there holden for the county of Berks, before the Right Honourable Sir Edward Turner, Knight ... and Sir Edward Thurland, Knight ... by Joseph Sayer ...</title>
                  <author>Sayer, Joseph, 1630 or 31-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98638:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Reading, Feb.</hi> 25. 1672.
AT THE ASSIZES
There holden for the County of <hi>BERKS,</hi>
Before the Right Honourable
Sir <hi>EDWARD T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER,</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Chief Baron;
And Sir EDWARD THURLAND Knight,
One of the Barons of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Court of Exchequer.</p>
            <p>By JOSEPH SAYER, B. D.
Rector of <hi>NEWB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> MDCLXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98638:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98638:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Rom. 13. part of the 5th Verſe,</hi> Wherefore ye muſt needs be Subject.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not without great cauſe that the firſt Preachers of the Goſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> the bleſſed Apoſtles, did inſiſt ſo very much upon, and did preſs with ſo much earneſtneſs, the Inferiours duty to his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour. For they having preached a liberty in Chriſt Jeſus, ſome licentious Spirits began thereupon to think themſelves free from all acts of ſervice and obedience to their Governours; thus abuſing their Chriſtian freedom to the great ſcandal and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Chriſtian Faith, by making it a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the fleſh. Hence the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> gives a large Exhortation in theſe words:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake; whether it be to the King as Supreme, or unto
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98638:3"/>Governours as unto them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well: that in ſo doing, you may have your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation honeſt among the Gentiles, that whereas they ſpeak evil of you as of evil doers, they may by your good works which they ſhall ſee, glorifie God in the day of viſitation. For ſo is the will of God, that by well-doing you may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men. As free, and not uſing your liberty for a cloak of maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but as the ſervants of God.</hi> In which words the Apoſtle plainly inſinuates, that there is no ſuch inconſiſtency between the Magiſtrates Authority, and our Chriſtian Liberty, as ſome might think there was. That they might, yea and ought to maintain the one, and yet withal ſubmit to the other. That it were a ſhameful abuſe of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and a very great diſhonour to our Chriſtian Profeſſion, under pretence of being Chriſtians, to refuſe to do the duty of Subjects. That Chriſt meant not to erect a Kingdom that ſhould deſtroy, or but diſturb the Kingdoms of this World; but to confirm them rather, by injoyning Obedience upon ſtricter obligations, and ſeverer penalties than were formerly thought of; ſuch as are the declared will and pleaſure of Almighty God, under the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of his eternal wrath and damnation. That the Liberty to which he calls the Subjects of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98638:3"/>ſpiritual Kingdom, is a Liberty like his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; 'tis a ſpiritual, not a ſenſual freedom; 'tis a freedom to ſerve God, not a freedom from the ſervice of men. That Chriſtians, as being all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kings, are to rule over their own luſts, and not live according to their luſts, denying Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Obedience unto Temporal Princes; for that were to make their Liberty become a cloak for their maliciouſneſs, or their covetouſneſs or licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs. And as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſo his dear Brother this moſt bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> not only charges it on his ſon <hi>Titus,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>put men in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, and to obey Magiſtrates;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> but he does it alſo himſelf in this Chapter,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> And not only minds them of their duty, but preſſes it with ſuch variety of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that in the whole Book of God there is ſcarcely any one duty that is preſt with ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and importunity as this is: Which does ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, both the great neceſſity of the thing, and our averſeneſs thereunto: that by Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> Nature corrupted, we can brook no Government; for who is willing to be ruled? and yet bear it we muſt, a neceſſity is laid upon us, we <hi>muſt needs be ſubject,</hi> and that for theſe reaſons: Becauſe</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we reſpect the Original, Fountain, or Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98638:4"/>Cauſe of Government, it has God for its Author. That's the Apoſtles firſt Argument for Subjection and Obedience to all Humane Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, taken from the Author, Founder, Inſtituter and Ordainer of ſuch Authority.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no Power but of God.</hi> The perſon ruling may be ſometimes ſuch a one, as that we cannot ſay he is of God. God by his Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> does complain of ſome Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, <hi>They are ſet up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>but not by me;</hi> their way of coming to the Government is by ſuch means as God prohibits. And the uſe of the Power may be as bad as the coming by it; as in King <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> who abuſed his Authority in <hi>making Iſrael to ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 14.16</note> 14.16. But the Power it ſelf is always of God, and he that comes to it lawfully is ſent of God, and therefore to ſuch we <hi>muſt needs be ſubject.</hi> For ſhan't we own that Power that has God for its Author?<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> Magiſtracy is the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> Magiſtrates are the <hi>Ministers of God,</hi> therefore it is our duty to be ſubject to it, and them. This is the Apoſtles firſt Argument for Subjection and Obedience to Authority, taken from the Author of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Argument is taken from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and comelineſs of order: whence God himſelf has his Title;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33, 40.</note> He is the God of order; <hi>He is the Author not of confuſion, but of peace.</hi> And he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98638:4"/>has declared it to be <hi>his will that all things be done decently and according to order,</hi> which is the beauty of Nature, the ornament of Art, and the harmony of the World; without which it can no more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, than the body can without a due tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the humours. Now <hi>the Powers that be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>are ordained of God.</hi> God has ordered them as they are. He has not only or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them, <hi>i. e.</hi> inſtituted and appointed them, as we commonly underſtand the word; but by him they are ſet in order, and diſpoſed into ſeveral ranks, as it more properly ſignifies. He ſets up Kings in the higheſt place, giving them the <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy;</hi> and under them he ſets up Judges, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> and ſubordinate Officers, to facilitate that work by the aſſiſtance of many, which would otherwiſe prove too heavy for any one mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Argument is taken from the evil of ſin, that is contracted by diſobeying. Not to obey the Power, is to ſin againſt Almighty God. 'Tis a violation of the Command of the Supreme Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver: <hi>Whoſoever reſiſteth the Power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>reſiſteth the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God.</hi> In oppoſing the one, he rebels againſt the other. He is a Rebel againſt God, that riſes up againſt his Prince, or makes any oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Governours that are ſent by him. The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98638:5"/>confederacy of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices <hi>againſt Moſes and Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.11</note> is called a <hi>gathering of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together againſt the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth Argument is taken from the evil of puniſhment that is incurr'd by diſobeying: <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or as we render it, <hi>damnation, i. e.</hi> according to the ordinary courſe of Gods Providence, they ſhall receive ſome grievous puniſhment here in this World.<note place="margin">Prov. 17.11.24.22.</note> 
               <hi>A cruel Meſſenger ſhall be ſent againſt them,</hi> and <hi>their deſtruction ſhall come ſuddainly.</hi> God for the moſt part being more quick, and more ſevere in revenging thoſe Injuries and Indignities that are offered to his Deputies, his Lieutenants, his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents here on earth, than thoſe greater and more hainous crimes that are committed more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately againſt Himſelf. He has declared it to be his will,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.12, 13.</note> that <hi>if any man will do preſumptuouſly, and will not hearken to the Prieſt and to the Judge, that man ſhall die, and ſo evil ſhall be put away from Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and ſo the people ſhall hear and fear, and do no more preſumptuouſly.</hi> We now live in an Age, when 'tis ſcarce thought to be a ſin not to hearken to the Judge or to the Prieſt: but you ſee how God accounts it, and what proviſion he has made for ſuch ſinners; even temporal deſtruction; <hi>that man ſhall die, i e.</hi> he ought to be put to death,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98638:5"/>And ſince God has declared it to be ſin, he that dies in it without repentance ſhall in the world to come ſuffer death everlaſting; that's the full import of the phraſe, <hi>They ſhall receive to themſelves dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> An inſtance whereof we have in <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices, who for their ſtubborn and ſeditious carriage towards <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.30 Pſal. 55.15.</note> 
               <hi>went down quick into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A fifth Argument is taken from the end for which Magiſtracy was ordained; <hi>viz.</hi> the benefit of Humane Society, the good of all Mankind, that by an equal diſtribution of rewards and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, Peace may be preſerved, Mens rights defended, Religion protected, Vertue incouraged, and Vice ſuppreſt. This is what's contained in the two Verſes next immediately preceding my Text Now from all theſe ſeveral reaſons, we have here the Apoſtles concluſion in my Text, That Subjection to Authority is the Chriſtians Duty. All theſe things conſidered, we <hi>muſt needs be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is a neceſſity of being ſubject.</p>
            <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly ſignifies to be <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate;</hi> It extends both to the State of Subjection, and to the exerciſe of the Subjects Duty, as St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> well obſerves. And as to Duty, it includes whatſoever Duty or Service may be challenged by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98638:6"/>Superiours at the hands of Inferiours. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that we obſerve the order wherein God has ſet us, and that we walk orderly, that we keep to the ſtation of Subjects, and that we do as does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Subjects.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak more diſtinctly; theſe particular Duties are included in this general. In the <hi>firſt</hi> place,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Being a Subject to keep the rank of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, to be content with our own ſtation, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſubmit our ſelves to that ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life to which God in his good pleaſure has deſigned and appointed us.<note place="margin">Phil. 4 11.</note> 
               <hi>I have learnt, ſays</hi> holy <hi>Paul, in whatſoever eſtate I am therewith to be content.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> And, <hi>Let every man abide in that calling wherein he is called with God,</hi> ſays the ſame Apoſtle <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> times in one Chapter. The better to underſtand his meaning there, you may do well to obſerve that the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.3.</note> being as yet but <hi>Carnal,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells them, having generally more of the Fleſh than of the Spirit, more of lg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Corruption, than of Grace and Knowledge, miſtook their Chriſtian Calling to be an exemption from the Duties of other Callings; as if their Liberty in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> had cancelled all precedent Obligations, both of nature and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary agreement: ('Tis that which I intimated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98638:6"/>in the entrance of this Diſcourſe:) The Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band would put away his Wife, the Wife reject her Husband; Children diſreſpect their Parents, Servants diſregard their Maſters, and themſelves become too maſterly. In a word, all perſons of what rank or condition ſoever, were apt to break the bonds of thoſe relations in which they ſtood obliged one to another, all under this pretence, and on this ground, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> by the introduction of his Goſpel, and their reception of it, had made them free. Now in this paſſage the holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> does deſignedly correct this errour: prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally indeed, and as the preſent Argument led him, in the particular of Marriage; but with a further and more univerſal extent to all ſtates and conditions of life. The ſum of what he ſays is this; that they who are any way related unto others, notwithſtanding that they are Chriſtians, muſt ſtill own their relations, and continue to perform all Offices ſuitable; though the perſons to whom they bear thoſe relations, are meer Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Infidels, Heathens and Unbelievers. The Wife muſt be contented with the condition of a Wife, and as a Wife ſhe muſt behave her ſelf to her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, though an Infidel. The Servant muſt content himſelf with the condition of a Servant, and as a Servant muſt behave himſelf towards his Maſter,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98638:7"/>though an Unbeliever. And in like manner a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject muſt content himſelf with the condition of a Subject, and as a Subject muſt behave himſelf towards his Sovereign, though a Pagan, though a Tyrant, though a Perſecutor; the relation which they had to <hi>Chriſt</hi> being not deſigned to weaken, and make void, but to ſtrengthen thoſe relations in which they ſtood obliged one to another, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther natural, or induced by contract and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The general Rule to this purpoſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives in form of an Exhortation: That every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, notwithſtanding that relation which he bears to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the freedom which he has by him, ſhould abide in that ſtation wherein God has placed him, keep himſelf within the bounds and limits thereof, and with a quiet and religious care, cheerfully and contentedly undergo the Duties that pertain thereto.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.17.</note> In few words, <hi>As God has diſtributed to every man, and as he has called every man, ſo let him walk.</hi> And for fear leſt his Exhortation to this purpoſe, being unſuitable to what they were very much inclined to, might be leſs heeded than 'twas neceſſary it ſhould; that he might recommend it ſo much the more both to their obſervation and practice, he does inforce it a ſecond time,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>Let every man abide in the ſame cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wherein he is called.</hi> And again once more,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98638:7"/>
               <hi>Brethren, let every man wherein he is called therein abide with God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.24.</note> This the Learned and moſt Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> has obſerved to be the ſcope and drift of the place, and the deſign of all theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inſtructions, Precepts, or Exhortations. You have the like Precept from the Apoſtle elſewhere, <hi>Study to be quiet, and meddle with your own buſineſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.11</note> Let every man attend that work to which the great Diſpoſer of all things has been pleaſed to ſet him. Let him carefully contain himſelf within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of his own calling, without aiming at high things, or intermedling with that which is the Province or concern of other men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Second</hi> ſpecial Duty included in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, is to render all due Honour, and that in thought, word, and deed, both to the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to the Perſon of our Superiour: For theſe two, Power and Perſon, cannot be divided; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them we may, ſo we do it to better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe than ſome have done it in our days: I ſay, diſtinguiſh them we may, but ſever them we may not. The Power exiſts in the Perſon, and we are to honour the Perſon with reſpect to his Power; as <hi>St. Peter</hi> teaches us, <hi>Fear God, honour the King;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> not the Power abſtracted from the Perſon, but the Perſon for the ſake of his Power. And ſo here in the ſeventh Verſe of this Chapter,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Render unto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98638:8"/>all their dues,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, ſpeaking to Subjects with reſpect to thoſe that have Authority over them; particularly, <hi>Honour to whom Honour is due.</hi> Now in the <hi>firſt</hi> place,</p>
            <p n="1">1. One part or branch of this Duty is to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour theſe in our thoughts,
<list>
                  <item>By thinking honourably of their Perſons,</item>
                  <item>By judging charitably of their Actions.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt have honourable thoughts of what they are. What the Apoſtle ſometime ſaid to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> with reſpect to himſelf and other Preachers of the Word,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>So account of us as of the Miniſters of Chriſt;</hi> may be ſaid to every Subject with reſpect to Kings, and ſuch as bear the Sword. You are to account of them as of the <hi>Miniſters of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> for ſo the Scripture calls them in the Verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Text. You are to eſteem of them, as of thoſe that are ordained of God for the <hi>good</hi> of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society, as in the ſame Verſe. You muſt not look on them as meer men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.1, 6.</note> but as <hi>Humane Gods,</hi> Pſal 82 1, 6. as the Deputies, Lieutenants, and magnificent repreſentations of the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; as thoſe whom God hath intruſted, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his room, to repreſent his Perſon, and to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98638:8"/>his Judgments, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.8. and again,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 9.8 19.6.</note> Chap. 19.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt have charitable thoughts of what they do; put the beſt, and not the worſt conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on the Laws they make, and the execution of thoſe Laws. If any thing ſeem harſh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient in their menage of affairs, we muſt give them their due honour by judging candidly and favourably of it; conſidering with our ſelves, that they have reaſons of State for what they do, whereof we are ignorant. 'Tis injoined us,<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>Not to curſe the King in our thoughts,</hi> i. e. neither to wiſh ill to him, nor to think ill of him. This Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive does include an Affirmative, that we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to entertain good thoughts of the King and of his Government. If every thing does not go as we would have it; If other Laws be enacted, or Laws otherwiſe executed than according to our phancy or judgment, we are apt preſently in our ſecret thoughts to condemn our Rulers of impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, inſincerity, injuſtice, partiality, cowardize, or the like; when in the mean time the greatneſs of their Authority, and our neceſſitated ignorance and unacquaintance with State-Affairs, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain our thoughts from ſuch harſh and haſty cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in things we do ſo little underſtand: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as unfit for private perſons to cenſure their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98638:9"/>as it is for little Children, that have newly learnt their Primer, to take upon them to correct the learnedſt Scholar. Let me give you but one inſtance, and I beſeech you note it: Suppoſe you had been preſent when <hi>King Solomon</hi> was deciding the controverſie between the two Mothers about the dead and living Child: When he called for a Sword to have the living Child divided in two, that ſo each Mother might have a part; would you not have thought him a very raſh, cruel, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Prince? Would you not have ſaid within your ſelves, What will this young King now do? Will he cut this knotty cauſe in pieces, becauſe he can't untie it? And for as much as there is no evidence unto which of the two Mothers the Child belongs, ſhall the Child be therefore ſlain? and becauſe one Murther was committed accidentally, ſhall another be done purpoſely? What a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable people are we like to be, that are to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a Prince! Thus perhaps you would have thought; whereas if you had ſtaid the iſſue of things, you would have ſeen his prudence, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired it, and have changed your mind of him, as the <hi>Barbarians</hi> did of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> when they ſaw the Viper on his hand,<note place="margin">Act. 28.4.</note> they concluded that <hi>he was a Murtherer, whom though he had eſcaped the Sea, Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance would not ſuffer to live;</hi> but when he ſhook
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98638:9"/>the Viper without hurt to himſelf from his hand into the fire, <hi>they ſtraight changed their mind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 28.6.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaid that he was a God.</hi> The King gave order for that which he had no deſire ſhould be done, only to find out that which could not otherwiſe be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; as you may ſee at large in the <hi>third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the <hi>firſt</hi> Book of <hi>King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 3.16. to the end of the Chapter.</note> This may warn us not to entertain hard thoughts of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, when at firſt bluſh we are unable to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile their Actions or Expreſſions to the ſtricteſt rules of Piety, Juſtice, Prudence or Charity.<note place="margin">Prov. 25.3.</note> 
               <hi>The Kings heart is a depth unſearcbable,</hi> Prov. 25.3. The Actions of wiſe Princes are meer Riddles to vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar apprehenſions; neither is it for the ſhallow capacities of the multitude to fathom the deep pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Sovereign Authority. And as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fathom them, ſo they ought not to cenſure them. If <hi>Charity thinketh no evil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5, 7.</note> but <hi>doth hope all things,</hi> even of all ſorts and conditions of men; then certainly it ſhould moſt of all do ſo by Kings, who <hi>miniſtring for our good,</hi> do deſerve the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt meaſure of our love.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Second</hi> part or branch of this Duty, is to honour them in our words, both when we talk
<list>
                  <item>to them.</item>
                  <item>of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98638:10"/>
1. When we talk to them, our words muſt make it appear that we reſpect and honour them: We muſt give them their due Titles, and we muſt ſpeak to them after a different manner from our way of ſpeaking to other men. Take an inſtance of it in holy <hi>Paul;</hi> when <hi>Feſtus</hi> upbraided him with <hi>madneſs,</hi> he did ſhew how much he honoured him for the ſake of his Authority; he did make no unhandſom, no uncivil retort to that ſevere and groundleſs imputation, but addreſt himſelf thus,<note place="margin">Acts 26.25.</note> with an humble reverence, <hi>I am not mad, moſt Noble Feſtus, but I ſpeak forth the words of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſs and truth.</hi> We have a like inſtance in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.27</note> 
               <hi>My Lord the King is as an Angel of God:</hi> And 'tis very obſervable, that he ſpake this at a time and in a caſe wherein the King had done him little right, and lately before had done him very great injury. But whatſoever the Kings dealing was towards him, yet he ſpeaks not but with great reverence and reſpect to the King: 'Twas far from him to ſpeak any thing to the Kings diſhonour; to upbraid him with incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderateneſs, with injuſtice, or with oppreſſion; though he had evident cauſe for it, if there could be any cauſe for a Subject to treat his Prince with any irreverence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we talk of them, it muſt be to their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98638:10"/>honour, ſpeaking of all the good that is in them, and of the good that is done by them. Thus did <hi>David</hi> by <hi>King Saul,</hi> who was his enemy, and who without any cauſe ſought to take away his life; even then, and ſo all the while he lived, it was <hi>David</hi>'s ſtile to call him, <hi>The Anointed of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24 6, 10.26.9, 11.16.23.</note> When he was dead, he did likewiſe; nay, he mourned for him, and lamented him in theſe words, <hi>Ye Daughters of Jeruſalem, weep over Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.14, 16, 24.</note> 
               <hi>who cloathed you with Scarlet, and other delights, and put ornaments of gold upon your apparel.</hi> After the ſame manner did King <hi>David</hi>'s Subjects ſpeak of him, even after he had made himſelf in famous by moſt horrible ſins, and them miſerable by Gods Judgments on thoſe ſins; yet even then they paſt by all the evils he had done, and they ſuffered, and remembred only the good they had received by him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.9.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.9.</note> 
               <hi>The King ſaved us out of the hands of our Enemies, and delivered us out of the hands of the Philiſtims.</hi> In which words alſo 'tis obſervable, that though they had done their parts every way towards the obtaining thoſe Victories and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, yet they aſcribe them not to themſelves, but unto him.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> In the Chapter immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they ſhewed what a value they had for their King; they declared that <hi>he was worth ten thouſand of themſelves;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.17</note> and again they call'd him <hi>the Light of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98638:11"/>Iſrael.</hi> But though they ſhewed this eſteem of <hi>David,</hi> who notwithſtanding his faults, was in the main a very excellent Prince; yet perhaps they thought and ſpake of others as they deſerved. Nay, they ſpake of the very worſt of their Kings not without honour and reverence: Was there a worſe than <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> who filled up the meaſure of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahs</hi> iniquity, and whom God liked ſo ill, that he thought fit to have no more of that Linage? Yet even him the Church called <hi>the Breath of her No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4.30.</note> and lamented that <hi>he was fallen into the Pits of her Enemies.</hi> They were concerned, as if their Life had depended on his; as in truth it did: Not the life of individual perſons, but the life of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Nation, and the well-being of all perſons in it, doth depend on that of their King. Though their King be none of the beſt, yet better have ſuch, than have none at all. If there were no King, men would live as if there were no God: every man that has ſtrength would be a King; yea, and more than a King, he would be a Tyrant over his weaker Neighbour; and is it not better to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the luſts of one Tyrant, than to the luſts of a thouſand? Better ſtand in awe of one man, than be afraid of every man? A ſevere and cruel Governour, though he do ſome particular wrongs, yet he ſerves for the protection of his Kingdom in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98638:11"/>general. Some few of his Subjects may perhaps ſuffer by his cruelty, but the generality of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are defended by his Power; are defended from the Invaſion of foreign Enemies, and from thoſe greater cruelties, which if it were not for him, they would one exerciſe over another. 'Tis a very true and a very excellent expreſſion, which I find uſed by a perſon of great Learning and Authority, That <hi>the little Finger of Licentiouſneſs is heavier than the Loins of the ſevereſt Laws, and ſtricteſt Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Third</hi> part or branch of this Duty is to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them in our Actions;
<list>
                  <item>By Yielding them all due Reverence.</item>
                  <item>By Rendring them their due Maintenance.</item>
                  <item>By Affording them our beſt Aſſiſtance.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are to honour thoſe in Authority by yielding them all due Reverence. They are <hi>Civil Gods,</hi> and are therefore to be worſhipt with a Civil Worſhip. It is ſaid of <hi>Davids</hi> Subjects, that <hi>they bowed down their heads,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.30.</note> 
               <hi>and worſhipped the Lord and the King;</hi> God with a Divine Worſhip, the King with a Humane Worſhip: They bear rule over our body, and muſt therefore have the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of our body. When <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> came before <hi>David,</hi> he <hi>fell down to the earth upon his face before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98638:12"/>the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.28 14.33.</note> 2 Sam. 18.28. Yea, his own Son <hi>Abſalom</hi> did as much, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.33. <hi>David</hi> did the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.4.</note> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 28 4. Such honour muſt be given where 'tis due; and 'tis due to thoſe that are in Gods ſtead, to do Juſtice among the Children of Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are to honour thoſe in Authority by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring them their due Maintenance. We are to <hi>honour God with our ſubſtance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3.9.</note> and in like manner we are to honour thoſe that are in ſtead of God. <hi>Tribute muſt be given where 'tis due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.7.</note> as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 7. and 'tis due to the King, as the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> in his Goſpel has taught us, both by his Doctrine and Example; for he himſelf paid Tribute to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> and rather than not do it,<note place="margin">Matth. 17.</note> he wrought a Miracle to do it, that he might convince the World of the abſolute neceſſity of it. And obſerving the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute-money, on which <hi>Caeſars</hi> Image and Superſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption was, he thus anſwered thoſe that tempted him,<note place="margin">Matth. 22.17, 21.</note> and propoſed this Queſtion to him, <hi>Is it lawful to give Tribute to Caeſar or not? Render un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods.</hi> And here 'tis very obſervable, that our Saviour does not ſay in the caſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; not <hi>give,</hi> but <hi>render.</hi> What we part with to the uſe of our Prince, is not to be lookt on as the peoples alms, but as the Princes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98638:12"/>juſt due; 'tis not a meer gratuity, but a debt: He has a right and title to it, and as ſuch we ought to part with it; and not only part with it as ſuch, but be cheerful in our parting with it; not pay it as we would another mans debt, but as an honeſt man would pay his own debt, when he has made great profit by the money that was lent him; <hi>i. e.</hi> pay it with as great a willingneſs as he had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in borrowing it. And this difference is obſerved not only by the curious, but by ſerious and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Writers, as particularly Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Text, between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a word that might have been uſed, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word which our Saviour rather choſe to uſe; the one takes in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is contained in the other, and does withal imply a readineſs, a frankneſs, and a cheerfulneſs in the Giver.</p>
            <p>Princes are ordained of God for the good of thoſe committed to their charge;<note place="margin">Rom. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>they attend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually on this very thing,</hi> and <hi>for this reaſon pay we Tribute to them,</hi> as in the next Verſe after my Text. They defend us from Enemies abroad, they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Robbers, and redreſs injuries at home: The adminiſtration of Juſtice, the ſecurity of our Lives, the quiet and peaceable poſſeſſion of our goods, are from them under God. Men look a skew on the Incomes of Princes, but conſider not their vaſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98638:13"/>Expences: Judges, Councellors, Officers of State, a continual Guard, ſending forth Embaſſadors, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the well-deſerving for univerſal incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, the maintaining of Navies by Sea, and Armies by Land, according as need requires, and infinite the like occaſions, cannot be diſcharged without great Treaſure, which is the ornament of Peace, and Sinews of War.</p>
            <p>Beſide that, a King ought to be maintained as a King, and his great care does deſerve a very great reward. 'Twas an Adagial Saying among the Jews, which our Saviour brought into his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.7.<note place="margin">Luc. 10.7.</note> that <hi>The Labourer is worthy of his Hire.</hi> And to detain the Labourers Wages, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud him of his Hire, has been ever reckoned as a ſin of the firſt rank, and of the higheſt degree. The Apoſtle St. <hi>James</hi> calls it <hi>a crying ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4. The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> denounces a <hi>Wo againſt him that uſes his Neighbours ſervice without wages,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 22.13.</note> Jer. 22.13.<note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> And in <hi>Mal</hi> 3.5. God has threatned that <hi>he will be a ſwift witneſs againſt thoſe that defraud the Hireling in his wages.</hi> Cuſtom and Tribute are the Kings Wages for the Work he does us; they are the Hire of his ſervice: God has appointed him his <hi>Work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.6 7.</note> and has aſſigned him his <hi>Wages</hi> alſo: To defraud him therefore of it, is a kind of theft; yea, the higheſt degree of theft, worſe than picking
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98638:13"/>of Pockets, or rifling of Houſes, or robbing on the High-ways; 'tis a theft from the whole Kingdom, which may be, and is many times indangered by it. The Kings buſineſs is to defend us; but if we defraud him of his due, we diſable him from it. And ſurely if men did but conſider what are the cares and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, what the toils and labours of that high and ſacred Calling; how many ſharp thorns are interwoven in every Crown, they would find very little cauſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy the Prince his due. A conſcientious care ought to be taken in the levying of Taxes, that the rich mans burthen be not careleſly or wilfully laid on the weaker ſhoulders of the poor: But whatſoever is their juſt proportion, muſt be paid, even by the poor if they are able; and that out of conſcience, not grudgingly or of neceſſity, but of a ready mind, and with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cheerfulneſs: conſidering that it is not the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs of Princes to impoſe Taxes for the gratification of their own will and pleaſure, but it is the holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God for the common good and ſafety both of Prince and People; and that it were a moſt une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual and moſt unreaſonable thing to expect the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Government and Laws, and not be willing and ready to contribute toward their maintenance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We are to honour thoſe in Authority by afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them our beſt aſſiſtance, the aſſiſtance of our <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt afford them the aſſiſtance of our <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and thoſe ſtrengthned and made effectual by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98638:14"/>juſt and holy converſation. 'Tis injoined us by St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1, 2</note> 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. that <hi>Supplications, Prayers; Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions, and giving Thanks, be made for all men, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for Kings, and all that are in Authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to what purpoſe is this injoined to wicked men? for we know that <hi>God heareth not the prayers of ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 9.31.</note> Joh. 9.31. And, <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, God will not hear my prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.18.</note> Pſal. 66.18. Yea, <hi>the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> or Prayer, <hi>of the wicked, is an abomination to the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 15.8.</note> Prov. 15.8. Therefore to the fervency of our Prayer, that it may be effectual, we muſt join godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and honeſty: for otherwiſe, while we ſeem to pray devoutly for our Prince, and in the mean time live ungodly and diſhoneſtly, our profane and wicked lives make our Prayers of none effect: our Prayers will not avail ſo much to preſerve him, as ſuch lives will be of force to undo him. It is no unuſual thing for the Subjects ſin to be the Princes ruine: ſo the Prophet told the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when God had firſt given them a King,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.25</note> 
               <hi>If you ſtill do wickedly, you ſhall be conſumed both you and your King.</hi> And they found the proof of it in the loſs of the beſt King that ever they had;<note place="margin">2 Chron. 35.24, 28.</note> I mean <hi>Joſiah</hi> that excellent Prince, who in the prime of his days was cut off for thoſe ſins that were not his, but his peoples: He had brought them to their Prayers, but thoſe Prayers could not be heard for the cry of their ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt afford them the aſſiſtance of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98638:14"/>We muſt not think much to expoſe our own Lives for the deſence and preſervation of theirs. We muſt ſtrive to the very utmoſt of our power, and with the utmoſt peril to our ſelves, to preſerve and to defend their Perſons, and with their Perſons all their Rights and Royalties, all their Dignities and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives. <hi>We are not to ſeek our own,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>but every one anothers wealth;</hi> yea, <hi>to lay down our lives one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.16.</note> We muſt be ready to do this for any one, but eſpecially for thoſe that have Authority over us, whoſe life and proſperity is of greateſt moment and concern both to our ſelves and to the whole Nation. Thus the people in <hi>Davids</hi> time were ready upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to ſtand between him and danger. In the War againſt <hi>Abſalom,</hi> when they drew out into the field, they engaged him by all means to abide in the City; for, ſaid they, <hi>Thou art worth ten thouſand of us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> And when afterwards in thoſe Wars againſt the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> King <hi>David</hi> was in danger of being ſlain by <hi>Iſhbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benob,</hi> who was Brother to the great <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath, Abiſhai</hi> ſtept in and <hi>ſuccoured him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.16, 17.</note> hazarding his own life to ſave the Kings; and not only ſo, but the whole Army of <hi>Iſrael</hi> made a vow among themſelves, that the King <hi>ſhould go no more into Battail,</hi> for fear of <hi>Quenching the Light of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Third</hi> ſpecial Duty included in this general, is to yield them obedience, and that both
<list>
                  <item>Active to their Precepts.</item>
                  <item>Paſſive to their Puniſhments.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98638:15"/>
We are to execute their Commands with cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to bear with patience what they inflict on us. In the <hi>Firſt</hi> place,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are to execute their Commands. It is our Duty to yield an active Obedience, both in things Civil, and in things Religious: but with this limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, while they command us nothing that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with our Duty toward Almighty God, <hi>i.e.</hi> nothing that God forbids. Whatſoever they do law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully command, we are in conſcience bound to obey it.<note place="margin">Defence of the Cure of Church-Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, <hi>p. 87.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What the Scripture does not make to be a ſin, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Command will make to be a duty:</hi> 'tis Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> expreſſion, whoſe teſtimony in this caſe ſhould me thinks prevail with thoſe who are leaſt affected with this moſt needful Doctrine of Obedience. And leſt perhaps it ſhould be thought, that he took up this Opinion but very lately; to them who ſhall read what he hath written, it will appear to have been his conſtant Opinion.<note place="margin">Theſ. 320.</note> That <hi>Rulers muſt be obeyed in all lawful things,</hi> is one of his <hi>Theſes</hi> in his <hi>Aphoriſms of Government.</hi> Nay, Kings and <hi>Magiſtrates muſt be Obeyed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ. 321.</note> not only in things Civil, but <hi>even about the Worſhip of God, in all lawful Commands,</hi> that his next <hi>Theſis,</hi> which he preſently thus explains: <hi>So much of the Circumſtances of Worſhip as God has left to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by men, we muſt obey the Magiſtrate in, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine them; and much more when he doth but enforce Gods own Commandments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 400. to 407.</note> Both there, and again more largely in his Book of <hi>Church-Government and Worſhip,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98638:15"/>he inſtances in the ſeveral circumſtances of Time, Place, Geſture, Veſture, and other Modes and Forms of Worſhip; of all which particular circumſtances he diſcourſes at large, and there tells us, <hi>that being left undetermined by the Word of God, and therefore left to be determined by the Laws of men, in all theſe we may be bound by the Commands of lawful Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, we are bound to obey the Magiſtrate not only in thoſe things which we know to be lawful, but in all thoſe things which we do not know to be ſinful. And ſo we are told by the ſame Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, as far as I can underſtand him, in theſe words: <hi>We muſt obey the Magiſtrate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ. 323.</note> 
               <hi>though we know not their Commands are lawful, ſo long as they are ſo indeed, and we have no ſufficient reaſon to believe them unlawful.</hi> This Doctrine he abundantly proves, both there and in ſeveral other places, (particularly in his Book of <hi>Church-Government and Worſhip</hi>) by ſuch Arguments as are not to be anſwered.<note place="margin">Pag. 461, 462, 484.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Gods Word commands Obedience to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in expreſs and down-right terms: <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you,</hi> Heb. 13.17.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Keep the Kings Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.2. <hi>Obey Magiſtrates,</hi> Tit. 3.1.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.2. Tit. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13. 1 Pet. 2.12. Tit. 3.1. 1 Pet. 2.15. Gal. 6.9. 2 Theſ. 3.13.</note>1 Pet. 2.13. It does reckon ſuch Obedience among the <hi>good works</hi> of the Goſpel, which a Chriſtian ſhould be always <hi>ready</hi> to perform, and calls it by the name of <hi>well-doing,</hi> of which a Chriſtian ought
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98638:16"/>not to be <hi>weary.</hi> If now the thing commanded by the Magiſtrate be not known to us to be as plainly forbidden, as this Duty of obeying what the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is pleaſed to command, is well known to be injoined by God, what excuſe can be had in the leaſt for our not obeying? Shall our own uncertain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, and but ſuſpitions only, be of ſo great weight and moment, as to prevail againſt a known and certain Command? Or ought not that much rather which is doubtful give way to that which is certain? the interpoſition of the Magiſtrates Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand being of ſo great weight and moment, as to render that a Duty, whereof we are not to doubt, which before we did not know, but did ſuſpect, or only doubt, to be a ſin. Holy <hi>Paul</hi> indeed has told us,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note> that <hi>Whatſoever is not of Faith, is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. <hi>i. e.</hi> Whatſoever we either do or forbear, without a reaſonable perſwaſion of the lawfulneſs of our ſo doing, or ſo forbearing, 'tis to us a ſin. And ſo again in the former part of that Verſe, <hi>He that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is damned if he eat, becauſe he eateth not of Faith.</hi> But withal we ought to know, that this Text of Scripture is to be underſtood only of thoſe things which are left to our own choice, being at liberty as we pleaſe, either to do or to forbear them. But it ſpeaks not of thoſe things wherein we are limited by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of thoſe that have Authority over us; whom to diſobey in things lawful, is ſin againſt Almighty God; and all ſin without repentance brings damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98638:16"/>upon our ſelves. Neither is it without great reaſon, that although we are to abſtain from a thing doubtful, being at our own diſpoſal free, and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined as to that particular; yet we both may and ought to do it, when Authority has injoined the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. I ſay not, but that if we have time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and means to inform our ſelves of the nature of the thing which is injoined, we ought firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and conſcientiouſly uſe thoſe means to inform our ſelves of the lawfulneſs of the thing, ere we do what is injoined us.</p>
            <p>But if our doubt be invincible, or the Command require ſo ſpeedy an Obedience, that we have not time, or cannot uſe means to reſolve it, in ſuch caſe the Command of our Superiour is enough to put an end to our doubting; our Superiour being Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, authorized and commiſſioned by him to reſolve us in ſuch doubtful caſes: ſo that his Command is a clear determining of the doubt; after which we are to doubt no more, while we continue in thoſe forementioned circumſtances; his Command being reaſon enough to make us own that thing to be our Duty, which as yet we do not certainly know, nor can abſolutely conclude to be a ſin. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe let it be obſerved what's recorded in <hi>Deut.</hi> chap. 17. verſe 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.<note place="margin">Deut. 17.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>If there ariſe a matter too hard for thee in judgment, between blood and blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween plea and plea, and between ſtroke and ſtroke, being matters of controverſie within thy gates: then ſhalt thou
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98638:17"/>ariſe and get thee to the place which the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe; and thou ſhalt come unto the Prieſts the Levites, and unto the Judge that ſhall be in thoſe days, and enquire, and they ſhall tell thee the ſentence of judgment. And thou ſhalt do according to the ſentence which they of that place (which the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe) ſhall ſhew thee; and thou ſhalt obſerve to do according to all that they inform thee; according to the ſentence of the Law which they ſhall teach thee, and according to the judgment which they ſhall tell thee, thou ſhalt do: thou ſhalt not decline from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which they ſhall ſhew thee, to the right hand or to the left. And the man that will do preſumptuouſly, and will not hearken to the Prieſt, (that ſtandeth there to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter before the Lord thy God) or unto the Judge, that man ſhall die, and thou ſhalt put away evil from Iſrael; and all the people ſhall hear and fear, and do no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, we are not only bound to yield Obedience in all thoſe thing which we know to be lawful, and in all thoſe things which we know not, but only ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be ſinful; but even in thoſe things which being lawful in themſelves (holy Scripture not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding them) we do verily think, by reaſon of ſome miſtake and errour of judgment, to be ſinful. We are ſtill under an Obligation of obeying, though in ſuch a caſe Obedience cannot be yielded without ſin. We are bound to obey, becauſe God commands it: The miſtake of our Judgment cannot diſoblige us from, nor diſpenſe with, the ſacred bond of Gods Precept.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98638:17"/>Sin can never free from Duty. The errour of our judgment is a ſin, and that can never change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a ſinful omiſſion, making that which is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its ſelf, become ſafe for us. Innocently impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to his duty, 'tis impoſſible any man ſhould be; and yet obeying in this caſe, we are ſure to ſin againſt God, becauſe we do that which we verily take to be ſinful: which does argue, that we would have done it, had it been really ſuch as upon miſtake we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it to be; and that therefore we have no fear of God before our eyes, in as much as we durſt adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on that, which we verily thought would be a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation of the Divine Law, and a provocation of Gods diſpleaſure againſt our ſelves; and therefore it is the ſame thing to us as if it had been really ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, a tranſgreſſion of the known Law of God: ſo that in ſuch a caſe, doing or not doing, obeying or not obeying, we are ſure to ſin againſt God: that's the great unhappineſs of an erring Conſcience. And yet there is no abſolute perplexity, for there is a third thing required, and to be done, and that is <hi>deponere erroneam conſcientiam,</hi> to lay aſide ones erroneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and miſtaken Conceptions: That is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy in ſuch caſes; to endeavour by an humble di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in the uſe of all proper and proportionable means to be truly and rightly informed; that ſo the Judgment may be purged from errour, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thereby freed from this deſperate neceſſity of ſinning.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98638:18"/>
But what if after ſerious endeavours, a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be convinced of the truth, cannot ſhake off his erroneous and miſtaken conceptions, cannot extri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate himſelf from the ſnare in which he is engaged? What is to be done in ſuch a caſe? He is to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it ſtill; having been ſerious in ſome degree al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, he muſt be yet more ſerious in his ſearch and ſtudy after the truth.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſ</hi> 6.3. <hi>Then ſhall a man know, when he follows on to know the Lord;</hi> when he ſeeks it again and again; <hi>ſeeks for it as for ſilver, and ſearches for it as for hid treaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 2.3.</note> Prov. 2.3. When he does perſiſt in the uſe of means, is exceeding earneſt in prayer to God for it, conſtant and indefatigable in his endeavours after it. He muſt be more willing to underſtand and embrace the truth, than he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that what he errs in ſhould prove true. He muſt lay aſide all prejudice and prepoſſeſſion, and muſt read and hear what's written, and may be ſaid, on the one ſide as well as on the other. And if he be biaſſed in any thing, it muſt be in an humble jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and miſtruſt of himſelf; and according to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> direction,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>in eſteeming others better than himſelf:</hi> and then,<note place="margin">Joh. 7.17.</note> according to our Saviours promiſe, <hi>he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whether it be of God or not.</hi> God will inſtruct and teach him, though not by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate revelation, (that is not to be lookt for now) yet by a particular ſecret and unknown aſſiſtance. <hi>The humble man ſhall have grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.5.</note> 1 Pet 5.5. <hi>The meek ſhall be guided in judgment, and ſhall be</hi> ſurely <hi>taught
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98638:18"/>Gods way,</hi> Pſal. 25.9.<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.9.</note> But the man that will not take this courſe, his continuance in errour becomes his greater condemnation, and may be lookt on as Gods judgment on him for his pride and partiality, for his negligence, diſreſpect to Authority, and for his want of care to be rightly informed.</p>
            <p>But what if a man has bound himſelf by Oath to do contrary to what the Law of his Prince Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands? Let Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> be heard in the caſe: <hi>An Oath does not bind,</hi> ſays he, <hi>againſt the wholſom Laws of the Commonwealth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe God hath commanded that every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers:</hi> it is in his Caſes of Conſcience concerning Oaths; this being the ſecond of thoſe ſix Caſes wherein he tells us that an Oath doth not bind. An Oath ought to be kept with all imaginable care and ſtrictneſs, and that in all things whatſoever that are not contrary to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Duty; but the intervention of a Duty ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedes the Obligation of an Oath. The voluntary Obligation which a man lays upon himſelf, cannot vacate that precedent Obligation that is laid upon him by the Lord. Surely God never meant that his Name ſhould be made uſe of in an Oath to oblige mens Conſciences to a violation of his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Let this horrible thought be once admitted, and men are at liberty to do what they liſt: they may change the nature of things; and may make it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yea neceſſary, to break all the Commands of God, and to commit all the ſins in the World. If a man be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98638:19"/>unwilling to perform ſome neceſſary Duty, as to pay his Debts, to relieve the Poor, to ſuſtain and honour his Parents, to keep the Lords Day holy, to frequent the place of Gods Publick Worſhip, to partake of the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper, or the like; 'tis but binding himſelf by Oath to the contrary, and he is diſcharged from what before was his Duty. And as for the omiſſion of Duties, ſo for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a mans Luſts; If a man ſcruple at Adultery, Inceſt, Theft, Murder, Sacriledge, Idolatry, Schiſm, Rebellion, or the like, 'tis but binding himſelf by Oath to do theſe things, and their nature being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately changed, he is to preſs them upon his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as obliging, neceſſary Duties. Once admit this errour, and you are furniſhed with an excuſe for whatſoever wickedneſs you have a mind to commit: 'Twill inſtruct you how to juſtifie all the ſins in the World, to the utter extirpation of all Religion, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Charity.</p>
            <p>Now in all theſe ſeveral inſtances, we are obliged to yi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld Obedience, though ſecured from any penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that might enſue upon our not obeying. The addition of a penalty to the preceptive part of the Law, being to extort Obedience from the careleſs and unconſcionable, the good man needs it not. It pertains not to the eſſence of a Law, that a penalty be joined with it, the form thereof conſiſting not at all in the Minatory, but in the Mandatory part of the Law; it being of equal force on the Conſcience,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98638:19"/>when it comes naked, and diſarmed of any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to inforce Obedience, as when dreſt up with all the terrours of a moſt ſevere and grievous inflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And he who fears the Lord, and makes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of what he does, will be obedient for Gods ſake, though he ſtand out of danger or fear of any puniſhment from man.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As in things lawful 'tis our Duty to yield an active Obedience to what the Magiſtrate is pleaſed to command, ſo to their puniſhments we are to yield a paſſive Obedience. In both theſe we have the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Gods ancient people in the profeſſion and promiſe of their Obedience to <hi>Joſhuah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 1.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>All that thou commandeſt us we will do, and whither ſoever thou ſendeſt us we will go: According as we hearkned unto Moſes in all things, ſo will we hearken unto thee. And whoſoever he be that doth rebel againſt thy Command, and will not hearken to thy words in all that thou commandeſt him, he ſhall be put to death.</hi> But for this part of paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>What glory is it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.20.</note> 1 Pet. 2.20. <hi>if, when you be buffetted for your faults, ye take it patiently?</hi> There is a higher degree of paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in ſubmitting to ſuffer for the not doing of thoſe things, in which we cannot with a good Conſcience yield an active Obedience. If you can find in your heart to ſuffer thus for a good Conſcience; and if, when you ſuffer thus, you take it patiently, <hi>this is acceptable before God,</hi> ſays the ſame Apoſtle in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of that Verſe. Thus did <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98638:20"/>it follows in the next Verſe;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> and thus all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians after his example; they will not only bear thoſe puniſhments which they juſtly ſuffer for their faults, but when puniſhed without cauſe, and againſt all rules of Juſtice, they will put up all ſuch wrongs with patience, when impoſed by lawful Authority. There is one only caſe, wherein the Magiſtrates Command ought not to be obeyed; and that is, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands things contrary to what Gods Word has plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded: But there is no caſe wherein his Power or Perſon may be reſiſted by force of Arms, or affronted with railing expreſſions. <hi>A King is one againſt whom there is no riſing up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30.31.</note> Prov. 30.31. He may not be contradicted, not ſo much as with a ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy word, in what he does to our diſpleaſure: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power; and who may ſay unto him, What doſt thou?</hi> 'Tis expreſly charged upon us, <hi>Not to revile the Gods, nor to curſe the Ruler of the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22 28</note> Exod. 22 28. which the Apoſtle in his quotation of it does thus explain,<note place="margin">Acts. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 23 5. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of the people.</hi> Evil ought not to be ſpoken of him; no, not though he do evil. <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to ſuffer, as did <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>Saviour,</hi> in whoſe ſteps they ought to tread; who, <hi>when he was reviled, he reviled not again, and when he ſuffered he threatned not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. 2.23.</note> 1 Pet. 2.23. Whoſoever they are that ſhall preſume to do the contrary, that holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is ſo far from allowing them the glorious Title of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that he will not own them to be men:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98638:20"/>They are Monſters without Reaſon, as well as void of all Religion. <hi>They that ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10, 12.</note> 
               <hi>and deſpiſe Government,</hi> ſays that bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bruit beaſts, made to be taken and deſtroyed,</hi> as not fit to live in any civil ſociety. Their doom there follows. <hi>They ſhall receive the reward of their unrighteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall utterly periſh in their own corruption.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all which, ſome men are never well but when they are taxing their Governours, and faulting the Government. It is meat and drink to them to be ſpeaking of the errours and miſcarriages of their Princes; many times finding fault when there is no fault truly to be found; or if there be a fault, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing it to all they meet; and by adding aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their own deviſing, making it ſeem worſe than indeed it is: this is the next ſtep to Rebellion. He that rails at his Prince, would reſiſt him if he durſt; and by ſpeaking ill of his Government, he but ſtirs up his fellow-ſubjects to wiſh, and when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerves, to aſſiſt him in its overthrow. If a Prince do that which is unjuſt or unbecoming, 'tis not for his Subjects ſawcily to upbraid him with it, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him for it: ſaid <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Job</hi> 34.18.<note place="margin">Job 34.18.</note> 
               <hi>Is it fit to ſay to a King, Thou art wicked; or to Princes, You are ungodly?</hi> No, it is not fit; it is very unfit, and what deſerves a very ſmart return of puniſhment. By the Law of God, <hi>He that curſed his Father or his Mother, was to be put to death,</hi> Exod. 21.17.<note place="margin">Exod. 21.17.</note> And can he deſerve leſs puniſhment, that ſhall dare to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98638:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>curſe the King, who is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> Father of his Country? He is much more worthy of it. <hi>Cham</hi> was curſed by his Father, and that curſe was ratified by God for uncovering his Fathers nakedneſs; but bleſſed were <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> for covering their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers nakedneſs, which their Brother had diſcovered and derided: They had their Fathers bleſſing, and the bleſſing of their heavenly Father; they were bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on Earth, and are bleſſed in Heaven. 'Tis our Duty to do the like; to conceal that, which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtifie; and what we cannot conceal, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as far as lawfully we may, without ſinning againſt Almighty God, by denying the fact, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the evil of it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all plain Scripture-Rules; and they, who walk according to theſe Rules,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>Peace be on them, and on the Iſrael of God.</hi> But whoſoever they are, that ſhall preſume to teach or do the contrary, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.6.</note> and ſeem never ſo good, <hi>Into their ſecret let not our Soul come.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98638:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
